DAN KLEIN: So here's that example of
map coloring that I promised you.
In map coloring, we've got some map.
And what we'd like to do
is make it colorful.
So we're going to assign a color to
different countries on the map.
And we want to make sure that adjacent
countries don't have the same color.
So in the recurring example we'll have
for today, the variables in this are
going to be the countries in the map.
And in this case, we're going
to be coloring in Australia.
And so they're actually called states.
So here are the states of Australia.
There's Western Australian in the west,
the Northern Territory in the
north, South Australia in the south,
Queensland up in the northeast, New
South Wales over in the east, Victoria
in the southeast, and then Tasmania is
some island that's disconnected
from the rest.
So here are our variables.
Make sure you kind of eyeball this for
a second now because we're going to
see this example over and over.
So here are our variables
in the problem.
What are the domains?
Well, they all have the same domain.
They can all take on either red,
green, or blue, if this is a
three-coloring problem here, and our
colors are red, green, and blue.
So this is going to be our
recurring example.
So what are the constraints?
If we just had variables and domains,
we could just color everything red.
And then we'd be happy.
But this wouldn't satisfy the constraint
that adjacent states have
to be different colors.
So if we want to have this constraint,
we need to write it down.
One way to write it down is what's
called an implicit constraint.
In an implicit constraint, we write
down a little snippet of what
basically amounts to code.
We write down some procedural way
of checking a constraint.
So one constraint-- for example, the
constraint on Western Australia and
the Northern Territory, which
are touching in the map--
we can write down that
they're not equal.
OK, this isn't a very heavy-duty
code snippet.
But this is something you would have to
evaluate to check to see whether or
not Western Australia and the Northern
Territory have a happy combination of
assignments.
We could also take this implicit
constraint, which is a constraint
between WA and NT.
And we could write it out explicitly.
So we could write down that the pair
WA, NT has to be contained in-- and
then we list a set of allowable values
in the cross-product of the domains.
So implicit means it's described
implicitly by a code snippet.
Explicit means we actually list
all of the allowed pairs
or triples or whatever.
What's a solution to this problem?
A solution is just an assignment that
satisfies all of the constraints.
So here's one.
This is the one that's shown.
Western Australia's red, the Northern
Territory's green, and so on.
So in order to be a solution, you have
to assign a value to every variable.
And all the constraints
need to be met.
That's map coloring.
Here's another example we'll
see a lot today.
This is the N-Queens problem.
So in the N-Queens problem,
we have a chessboard.
In this case, it's a four
by four chessboard.
And what we'd like to do is we'd like
to place N-- in this case, four--
queens on that chessboard in
a way that they aren't
threatening each other.
So if you know anything about chess, you
know that queens in the same row
can attack each other.
Queens in the same diagonal
And we'd like to be able to find a
configuration like the one shown where
nobody's threatening anybody else.
And it's all a wonderful,
peaceful kingdom.
So how are we going to do this?
Well, here's one formulation.
One formulation is we
need some variables.
So let's make the variables be each
square on the chessboard is going to
have a variable.
So we'll call those Xij.
And each of those variables is
going to indicate what's
happening on that square.
So what can be happening on a square?
It can either be queened or empty.
So we'll write that down.
0 will mean empty.
And 1 will mean that there's
a queen there.
OK, so there's variables.
There's the domains.
And an assignment can specify what's
going on on the board.
So far, we could just stick queens
everywhere, or nowhere.
So we need some constraints.
What are the constraints
in this problem?
Well, we know what they
mean intuitively.
Intuitively they mean that we
can't have any threatening
between a pair of queens.
So what we could do is we could pick
all of the squares that exist in a
threatening configuration.
For example, take any two squares
in the same row or column.
And we could write down a bunch of
constraints that look like this.
So for example, for a given i-- so
that's, say, in a fixed row--
we look at all columns j and k.
And we say for Xij and Xik, that pair
can only be assigned 0, 0--
meaning there's not a queen
in either square--
0, 1 or 1, 0, meaning exactly
one of them has a queen.
And you'll notice that what's
missing is 1, 1.
And that's because for one
value of i, j, and k--
that would be here and here.
And if they were both assigned 1, then
we would have a threatening pair.
And that would be invalid according
to our constraints.
So this set of constraints-- and
there's a bunch of them.
I wrote them-- there's
a quantifier there.
There's actually a bunch
of constraints.
This takes care of threatening
across rows.
We also need threatening across columns
and threatening across left
and right diagonals.
So we would get a bunch of
similar-looking constraints.
Basically, for any pair that can
threaten, we get a constraint on that
pair saying, you both can't be on.
This constraints are simple, but
there are a bunch of them.
OK, am I done?
Does satisfying these constraints
solve my problem?
I heard a no.
Why not?
For example, right now with these
constraints, we have a problem, which
is assigning 0 everywhere-- an empty
board-- satisfies the constraints.
We prevented threatening queens.
But we haven't made sure that
there are actually queens
anywhere on the board.
In particular, we haven't made sure
that there are N of them.
So we could also write down a constraint
that looks like this.
Over all i and j, the sum of Xij equals
N. Now, notice the constraints
on the left as I've written them
are explicit constraints.
The constraint on the right
is an implicit constraint.
You evaluate a snippet of code
in order to figure out
whether it's passed.
The constraint on the right would be
a pretty hard thing to write out
explicitly.
Here's another formulation
of N-Queens.
We'll see which one we like better.
So here's another formulation.
In this formulation, we
say, wait a minute.
Actually, we know, based on the
structure of the problem, that every
row has a queen somewhere.
So let's make a variable for each row.
So Q sub k will be where
the queen is in row k.
So for example, Q sub 1 here is
where the queen is in row one.
And it would take on the value
2 to indicate it's in the
column number two.
Here, the domains now are not 0 and 1.
They're not binary.
Or rather, they indicate a column.
So they'll go from 1 to N. We can
still represent a solution.
What about the constraints?
Well, constraints actually get
a little more difficult here.
For constraints, we could write out some
implicit constraints that say,
for example, for all i and j--
so for all pairs of rows--
we would look at those two rows.
And we'd figure out the non-threatening
constraint between them--
basically says, queen i and
queen j can't threaten.
And so we'd have to write that out and
say, OK, well, for rows one and two,
that means they can be in positions one
and three respectively, one and
four respectively, and so on.
And we could just list them.
So again, the implicit constraint here--
in this particular case, it's
probably easier to write
it out explicitly.
Because you know exactly what
the configurations are.
And there aren't that many
of them for a pair.
So two very different formulations.
The first one had more variables
but simpler domains.
The first one had more constraints
but simpler constraints.
Which one do you think is better?
So first of all, there are a lot
of ways to formulate constraint
satisfaction problems.
And in some cases, you don't actually
know which one's going to be better
until you try.
In this particular case, we would expect
formulation two to be better.
Because it encodes knowledge of the
problem, kind of by the structure of
the variables and constraints.
We know we're going to get
a queen in every row.
We're not going to get
two in every row.
And there are lot of things the other
problem is trying to enforce via
constraints and assignments that here
is just baked into the formulation.
And in general, that's going
to be an advantage.